So, we're going to wrap up this section talking
a little bit more about what we would do in order
to get the instructions, the machine language
instructions, instead of coming from a little
switch, which is completely fake, but instead
coming from the memory. And so to do that,
we look a little bit more into computer
architecture. We talked before about the ALU,
the arithmetic and logic unit, as well as the
registers. So the ALU has like an adder in it,
maybe a multiplier or a comparison module all in
hardware. Then we have registers which have you
know bits in them like numbers and their temporary
storage. And in addition, we're going to talk a
little more now about the logic. Now the load
and store the way we're going to do it goes to
and from registers for like data memory. But for
program memory, there's a couple of things that
the CPU uses to control program memory. So one
is the PC or program counter register. So this
is a register that points to the next instruction
we're supposed to execute. So you the CPU when
it's ready to execute an instruction that says oh
the PC tells me where to load it. So I'm going to
load that instruction from the memory into CIR
current instruction register. And that's just
some bits zeros and one. And then I mentioned the
idea of a decoder. And in the previous example,
we had some ANDgates that were in a sense our
decoder. So when you have a real CPU, it has a
lot more than two instructions. And the decoder is
looking at the pattern of bits in the instruction,
decoding it, and then sending logic to the ALU
in the registers to activate the right thing to
get the right thing to happen. So maybe we're
going to add two registers together and store
the result in a different register. Okay? And the
decoder sees that instruction that's that that is
the add two registers and store in another
register instruction. And then the decoder
sees the pattern of that and then it activates
the right registers, the right arithmetic logic
unit and then causes the instruction to happen in
one or a couple of clock cycles depending on how
difficult it is. In the previous example, we had
like a zero to reset and a one to add one every
clock cycle. So it incremented or it stopped went
to back to zero. But in reality you need a series
of machine language instructions like uh set
register 4 to zero, compare register 4 to zero,
increment register 4, decrement register 4. And
so there are binary patterns which are part of
the documentation of a microprocessor. So if the
decode unit looks at 0 1 0 0 for the instruction,
it says, "Oh, that's a zero instruction." And then
RR is three bits for a register from 0 through
7. So you're setting register three to zero.
And so these are just simple patterns and they
might seem really complex to you, but in some
ways they're actually really easy. The number
of things you can do in this machine language is
really limited. Now it makes programs a lot more
verbose and usually we have we don't even write
the zeros and ones. We write this stuff called
assembly which we'll talk about coming up or or
we write C which is a higher level language that
then generates assembly which generates machine
language or take a language like Python which
sort of almost completely separates us from
the machine language but then Python itself is
written in machine language so that it's really
fast. So, coming up next, we're going to design
a very simple central processing unit. I call
it the CDC 8512. Inspired by my first computer,
the Control Data Corporation CDC 6500. It'll
have a complete architecture. It'll be completely
defined. It'll have a program counter. It'll have
an instruction register. And we will write real,
very small programs in CDC 8512 machine
code and then run them on an emulator.